Guide to the George Folsom Papers 1821-1866 MS 222
New-York Historical Society
George Folsom papers
1821-1866
New-York Historical Society
Folsom, George, 1802-1869
MS 222
4.17 Linear feet (10 boxes)
Correspondence and a few papers, 1821-1866, primarily letters received by George Folsom (1802-1869) from authors, politicians, historians, artists, librarians, booksellers, and ethnologists. Included is material relating to family matters, his service as New York State Senator (Native American Party, or Know Nothings), 1845-1847, and chargé d'affaires to the Netherlands, 1850-1853, as well as his associations with the American Antiquarian Society, New-York Historical Society, and other learned societies.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Wesley A. Crozier, 1977.
Arrangement
The collection is housed in ten boxes. Boxes 1 through 9 are arranged chronologically by date of letter, or, when that is lacking, by date of postmark. Letters from select correspondents, which span several years, are grouped into distinct folders, and are filed after the general correspondence for their initial year. For example, the letters from Albert Gallatin, which span 1834-1844 (Box 2, Folder 7), follow the general correspondence for 1834 July-December (Box 2, Folder 6).
Box 10 includes correspondence that is undated and grouped by recipient (Folder 1, family), place (Folders 2-4, Maine, Massachusetts, and Europe), or by correspondent (Folders 5-6, arranged alphabetically). Undated letters and loose covers from unidentified correspondents are in Folder 7.
Biographical Note
In his long career George Folsom (1802-1869) adopted varied, interchangeable, and occasionally overlapping roles, among them attorney, historian, author, librarian, antiquarian, politician, diplomat, and ethnologist. He was a member (and sometime officer) of the American Antiquarian Society, New-York Historical Society, Maine Historical Society, Vermont Historical Society, American Geographical and Statistical Society, Athenaeum Association, Century Association, Union League Club, and American Ethnological Society, of which he was president for the last decade of his life. Most notably, he sat in the New York State Senate (1845-1847), and served as chargé d'affaires (the diplomatic official who heads an embassy in the absence of an ambassador) to the Netherlands (1850-1853).
Chronology
1802 May 23: Born in Kennebunk, Maine, to Thomas and Edna (Ela) Folsom.
1809 Moved to Portland, Maine. Educated there and at Phillips Academy, Exeter.
1822 Graduated from Harvard. Spent two years in the office of Ether Shepley of Saco, Maine; Shepley was then United States attorney for the District of Maine and later chief justice of the Maine Supreme Court.
1824 Admitted to the bar.
1830 Published History of Saco and Biddeford (Maine).
1831 October 24: Elected to membership in the American Antiquarian Society.
1836 Directed publication of the second volume of Transactions and Collections of the American Antiquarian Society.
1837 Moved to New York City to practice law.
1838 Lecture before the New-York Historical Society, "The Discovery of America by the Northmen in the 10th Century."
1839 Married Margaret Cornelia Winthrop (1800-1863), daughter of Benjamin and Judith (Stuyvesant) Winthrop of New York City. She descended from Peter Stuyvesant, last Dutch director-general of New Netherland, and John Winthrop, leading figure in the founding of the Massachusetts Bay Colony.
" Two lectures before the New-York Historical Society: "The Manuscript Parliamentary Journals in the Library of the Society" and "The Life and Voyages of Amerigo Vespucci."
1840-1841 Appointed librarian, New-York Historical Society. Edited Collections of the New-York Historical Society, second series, volume 1 (1841).
1842 Member of the Executive Committee, New-York Historical Society.
" Published Mexico in 1842.
" Birth of daughter, Margaret Winthrop Folsom (1842-1925).
1843 Domestic Corresponding Secretary, New-York Historical Society (1843-1844).
" Lecture before the New-York Historical Society, "Extracts from a Translation of the Official Narrative of Cortez to Charles V," in conjunction with publication of his English translation (the first) of The Despatches of Hernando Cortes.
" December 26: Birth of daughter Helen Stuyvesant Folsom (1843-1882), later known as Sr. Helen Margaret Folsom, founder of the American branch of the (Anglican) religious sisterhood, the Community of St. John Baptist (CSJB), a.k.a. the "Clewer Sisters."
1845 Elected Native American Party (Know Nothing) member of the New York State Senate (1st District), sitting in the 68th, 69th, and 70th New York State Legislatures (1845-1847).
1846 American Party candidate for Lieutenant Governor of New York (unsuccesful).
" Delivered anniversary discourse before the Maine Historical Society.
" August 20: Birth of son George Winthrop Folsom (1846-1915).
1850-1853 Served as chargé d'affaires to the Netherlands under Zachary Taylor.
1854-1857 Travels in Europe and the Holy Land.
1858 Published A Catalogue of Original Documents in the English Archives, Relating to the Early History of the State of Maine.
1858-1859 Editor in New York of Historical Magazine.
1859 Lecture before the New-York Historical Society, "The Life and Character of Col. Isaac Barre."
1859-1869 President, American Ethnological Society in New York
1860 Received honorary degree of Doctor of Law, University of Vermont.
1861 Donated portrait of General Anthony Wayne (1745-1796) to New-York Historical Society (museum accession no. 1861.4).
1863 March 18: Death of wife, Margaret Cornelia (Winthrop) Folsom.
1869 March 27: Died at Rome.
" May 4: Interred at St. Mark's-in-the-Bowery churchyard, New York.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society also holds
• Letter from George Folsom to Monseiur Poore (probably Benjamin P. Poore), dated Morley's Hotel, Trafalgar Square, London, 1843 October 24, regarding a place for a law student, a visit from Charles Magill Conrad, former senator from Louisiana, and publishing in "The Athenaeum," with a 25-page notebook containing Folsom's remarks on cases before the New York Court for the Correction of Errors during the May Term, 1846. Call phrase: AHMC - Folsom, George.
• Letter from George Folsom to George H. Moore, librarian of the New-York Historical Society, 1861 June 18, regarding Folsom's donation of a portrait of General Anthony Wayne (1745-1796) (see N-YHS museum accession no. 1861.4). Call phrase: AHMC - Wayne, Anthony.
• Consult the Manuscript Card Catalog to access Folsom's letters to Luther Bradish, 1844-1858 (call phrase: Bradish Papers) and Albert Gallatin, 1834-1845 (call phrase: Gallatin Papers).
• A number of Folsom's published works are held in the Printed Collections of the New-York Historical Society Library. His photograph is mounted at the front of In Memoriam, an 1871 biographical sketch by his daughter, Helen Stuyvesant Folsom. Call number: Pamph CT275.F65 F65 1871
The New York State Library holds two boxes of genealogical material and personal papers which include Folsom's college notebook and his attaché book from his service in the Netherlands.
Scope and Contents
The George Folsom Papers consist primarily of letters he received from an expansive network of historians, authors, librarians, scholars, ethnologists, geographers, clergymen, politicians, diplomats, club members, and family. They span from 1821 (the year before he graduated from Harvard) to 1866 (three years before he died at Rome). The chronology above is a guide to determining which of his myriad activities are likely to be referenced by the letters in a given year.
The collection includes extended correspondence from George Bancroft (1800-1891), American historian and statesman (Box 3, Folder 4); August Belmont (1813-1890), German-American politician, financier, and Folsom's successor as chargé d'affaires to the Netherlands (Box 8, Folder 4); John Romeyn Brodhead (1814-1873), American historical scholar (Box 4, Folder 3); Edward Everett (1794-1865), American politician, pastor, educator, diplomat, and orator (Box 2, Folder 4); Albert Gallatin (1761-1849), Swiss-American politician, diplomat, ethnologist and linguist (Box 2, Folder 7); Jared Sparks (1789-1866), American historian, educator, and Unitarian minister (Box 4, Folder 4); and Peter G. Stuyvesant (1778-1847), Folsom's uncle through marriage (Box 4, Folder 5).
Other items of note include an 1838 letter from Harvard librarian and Unitarian minister Thaddeus Mason Harris (1768–1842) regarding the first publication of the New-York Historical Society's manuscript copy of John Winthrop's 1630 sermon "A Modell of Christian Charity" (Box 3, Folder 7); an 1845 letter from geographer Henry R. Schoolcraft (1793-1864) regarding a census of the Native American population (Box 4, Folder 14); and an 1852 letter from artist and co-founder of the Metropolitan Museum of Art Eastman Johnson (1824-1906), who found the pictures in Florence somewhat disappointing (Box 7, Folder 6).
Invitations, receipts, and the occasional bookseller's prospectus are scattered throughout the collection.
Circulars (fliers).; Envelopes; Letters (correspondence); Receipts (financial records); Stationery; Art historians -- Correspondence; Diplomatic and consular service; Dressmaking; Indians Of North America -- Languages; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Librarians -- Correspondence.; Politics, Practical; Maine -- History.; Mexico -- History.; Netherlands.; New York (N.Y.); Stuyvesant Square (New York, N.Y.).; Vermont -- History.; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891; Belmont, August, 1813-1890; Benjamin, Park, 1809-1864; Brodhead, John Romeyn, 1814-1873; Burnside, Ambrose Everett, 1824-1881; Butterworth, J. F., active 1850; Carey, Mathew, 1760-1839; Carter, Nathaniel Hazelton, 1787-1930; Chapman, J. G. (John Gadsby), 1808-1889; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849.; Hamilton, A. J. (Alexander James), 1835-1897; Harris, Thaddeus Mason, 1768-1842; Harris, Townsend, 1804-1878; Hunt, Washington, 1811-1867; Hunt, William; Johnson, Eastman, 1824-1906; Kościuszko, Tadeusz, 1746-1817; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860; Perry, Matthew Calbraith, 1794-1858; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866; Stuyvesant, Peter Gerard, 1777-1847; Waring, George E., Jr. (George Edwin), 1833-1898; Wayne, Anthony, 1745-1796; American Antiquarian Society; American Ethnological Society; American Geographical and Statistical Society; American Party; Athenaeum Association (New York, N.Y.); Century Association (New York, N.Y.); Maine Historical Society; New-York Historical Society; Union League Club (New York, N.Y.); Vermont Historical Society
- Box 1: Letters, 1821-1832
  - Letters, 1821-1824 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    See 1825 March 4, from Nathaniel Hazelton Carter, a Dartmouth professor who lost his position after the Dartmouth College Case (a.k.a., Dartmouth College v. Woodward).
    See 1825 May 24, introducing Folsom to Stephen Longfellow, U.S. Representative from Maine.
  - Letters, 1826 February-August (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1826 October-December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1828-1829 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    See 1831 October 24, Folsom's certificate of election to membership in the American Antiquarian Society.
  - Letters, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Box 2: Letters, 1833-1835 (April)
  - Letters, 1833 January-April (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1833 May-June (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1833 July-December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Edward Everett, 1832-1852 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    On politics and the acquisition of a portrait of Hugo Grotius. Edward Everett (1794-1865) was an American politician, pastor, educator, diplomat, and orator.
  - Letters, 1834 January-June (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1834 July-December (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Albert Gallatin, 1834-1844 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    On Native American tribes and languages, and documents in London relating to the colonial history of New York. Refer to the Manuscript Department card catalog for Folsom's responses to Gallatin. Albert Gallatin (1761-1849) was a Swiss-American politician, diplomat, ethnologist and linguist.
  - Letters, 1835 January-April (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Box 3: Letters, 1835 (May)-1840
  - Letters, 1835 May-August (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1835 September-December (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1836 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters from George Bancroft, 1836-1850 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    On historical and literary matters. George Bancroft (1800-1891) was an American historian and statesman.
  - Letters on seamstresses, 1836-1837 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes two copies of a printed broadside, Order of Excercises, for the Public Meeting in behalf of the Tailoresses and Seamstresses' Benevolent Society, Wednesday Evening, December 28th, 1836, and three letters from Irish-American publisher and economist Mathew Carey dated 1837 (January 24, February 1, and February 7).
  - Letters, 1837 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1838 January-June (Box 3, Folder 7)
    See 1838 April 11, from Thaddeus Mason Harris, at Boston, to Folsom at the New-York Historical Society, regarding publication by the Massachusetts Historical Society of John Winthrop's 1630 sermon "A Model of Christian Charity." Harris (1768–1842) was a Harvard librarian and Unitarian minister.
  - Letters, 1838 July-December (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1839 January-June (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1839 July-December (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1840 January-June (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1840 July-December (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Box 4: Letters, 1841-1845 (March)
  - Letters, 1841 January-July (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1841 August-December (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letters from John Romeyn Brodhead, 1841-1843 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    From The Hague and London, reporting on Brodhead's progress in procuring material from European archives to fill gaps in New York State archives. John Romeyn Brodhead (1814-1873) was an American historical scholar.
  - Letters from Jared Sparks, 1841-1859 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    On historical and literary matters. Jared Sparks (1789-1866) was an American historian, educator, and Unitarian minister.
  - Letters from Peter G. Stuyvesant, 1841-1847 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Letters and some papers from New York City, mostly concerning the controversy surrounding the opening of Stuyvesant Square. Peter G. Stuyvesant (1778-1847) was the maternal uncle of George Folsom's wife, Margaret Cornelia (Winthrop) Folsom.
  - Letters, 1842 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1843 January-May (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1843 June-September (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1844 January-July (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1844 August-December (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1845 January (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1845 February (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1845 March 1-12 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1845 March 15-31 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    See 1845 March 31, from Henry R. Schoolcraft on a census of the Native American population, and the New-York Historical Society's committee on the subject of a new name for the United States. Schoolcraft (1793-1864) was an American geographer.
- Box 5: Letters, 1845 (April)-1846 (June)
  - Letters, 1845 April 1-12 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1845 April 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1845 May-June (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1845 July-December (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Folsom in Albany, N.Y., as senator, [1845-1847] (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1846 January-February 14 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1846 February 17-March 12 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1846 March 15-April (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1846 May-June (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Box 6: Letters, 1846 (July)-1848
  - Letters, 1846 July-December (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1847 January (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1847 February (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1847 March (Box 6, Folder 4)
    See 1847 March 2, from Townsend Harris, president of the New York City Board of Education, on the establishment of a "Free Academy," today's City College.
  - Letters, 1847 April (Box 6, Folder 5)
    See 1847 April [26], from William Hunt, at Lexington, Greene County, N.Y., requesting Folsom's personal details for inclusion in The New York Biographical Sketch Book, published in 1848 under the title The American Biographical Sketch Book. With prospectus and subscription form.
  - Letters, 1847 May-December (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1847 March-August (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1847 September-December (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Box 7: Letters, 1849-1852 (September)
  - Letters, 1849 January-June (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1849 July-December (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Letters, [1840s-1850s] (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1850 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    See 1850 January 8, from J. F. Butterworth regarding the establishment of a branch of the United States Mint in New York.
  - Letters, 1851 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1852 January-April (Box 7, Folder 6)
    See 1852 March 17, from Eastman Johnson, at Venice, on the rigors of his European travels and comments on art: "Florence is beautiful, tho. I was somewhat disappointed in its pictures. The more I see of old pictures the more humbug I find in them, & I have had a surfeit these past few days." Johnson (1824-1906) was an artist and co-founder of the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  - Letters, 1852 May-September (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Box 8: Letters, 1852 (October)-1855
  - Letters, 1852 October-December (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1853 January-May (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1853 June-December (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Letters from August Belmont, 1853-1856 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    On matters of transition and consular affairs. August Belmont (1813-1890) was a German-American politician, financier, and Folsom's successor as chargé d'affaires to the Netherlands.
  - Letters, 1854 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    See 1854 December 19, from painter John Gadsby Chapman, at Rome, on cholera there and the progress of pictures ordered.
  - Letters, 1855 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Box 9: Letters, 1856-1866
  - Letters, 1856 January-April (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1856 May-June (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1856 July-October (Box 9, Folder 3)
    See 1856 July 30, in French, from Paris, on stationery featuring a portrait of Tadeusz Kościuszko.
  - Letters, 1857-1859 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1860 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    See 1860 March 29, pictorial cover of the Delavan House [hotel], Albany, N.Y.
    See 1860 November 15, request to have Folsom's portrait painted for the Athenaeum Club. Signed by George E. Waring Jr. and others.
  - Letters, 1861 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1862-1863 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    See 1862 March 25, on stationery featuring a portrait of General Ambrose Burnside.
    See 1863 January 23, includes a carte de visite photograph of a mature woman.
  - Letters, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1865-1866 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Box 10: Letters to Folsom and family, undated
  - Undated, to Folsom and family (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Undated, to Folsom in Maine (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Undated, to Folsom in Massachusetts (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Undated, to Folsom in Europe (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Undated, from correspondents A-L (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Includes material from Park Benjamin Sr. (2 letters); Hamilton Fish (2 invitations); Mr. and Mrs. Alexander J. Hamilton (2 calling cards); and a letter from Washington Hunt, governor of New York, 1851-1852.
  - Undated, from correspondents M-Z (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Includes material from Rembrandt Peale (2 letters, one referencing Folsom's portrait of Revolutionary War General Anthony Wayne; see N-YHS museum accession no. 1861.4) and Commodore Matthew C. Perry (a note, in his hand, written on his calling card).
  - Undated, unidentified, loose covers, etc. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Includes a photocopy of In Memoriam, an 1871 biographical sketch by Folsom's daughter, Helen Stuyvesant Folsom. For original, request call number: Pamph CT275.F65 F65 1871.